Guide to the Thornton Wilder Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thornton Wilder papers
1892-1991
1935-1975
YCAL MSS 108
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
113.88
(211 boxes) + 9 broadside folders, 3 art storage items, cold storage, 1 record album storage
The collection consists chiefly of correspondence with family, friends, and literary colleagues; and writings, accompanied by related material. There are smaller amounts of personal papers, printed material, photographs, memorabilia, and audio recordings. The material documents Wilder's life and work, in particular his career as a successful novelist and playwright. Series I, Correspondence, consists of four subseries: Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; First Name Only and Unidentified Correspondence; and Third Party Correspondence. Wilder's correspondence with family members, notably with his sister Isabel, is extensive and contains much information on both his personal and professional activities. General Correspondence consists mainly of letters received by Wilder and particularly documents his literary activities and public reception after the success of Our Town in 1938. Correspondents include Garson Kanin, Michael Myerberg, Vivien Leigh, Louise Talma, Max Beerbohm, Vincent Sheean, Gertrude Stein, Glenway Wescott, and Herberth Herlitschka. Series II, Writings, contains excellent documentation of Wilder's works, including holograph and typescript drafts of all of his major writings; extensive materials relating to the production and adaptation histories of Our Town and The Skin of Our Teeth; and review and publicity files for both plays and novels. The series also holds drafts of many essays and lectures by Wilder, as well as copies of writings by others, most but not all Wilder-related. Series III, Personal Papers, includes journals, autobiographical notes and notebooks kept by Wilder; numerous awards and honors bestowed on him; papers relating to his education and career as a university lecturer; research notes on Finnegans Wake; his military service papers; and some financial and travel records. Series IV, Printed Material, consists of newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and an extensive run of theater programs for plays attended by Wilder and his sister Isabel. Series V, Photographs, primarily contains portraits of Wilder taken throughout his life, including some of his stage appearances and a variety of publicity shots. There are also photographs of family and friends and production photographs for several plays. Series VI, Memorabilia and Other Papers, contains artwork, other realia, and musical scores by Louise Talma and others. Series VII, Audio Tapes and Other Recordings, consists of a variety of sound recordings received with the Wilder Papers, including interviews and readings. Series VIII, Thornton Wilder Papers Addition, contains a small amount of family correspondence received after the collection had been processed.
Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Mainly gift of Thornton Wilder (Yale 1920) and the Wilder family, 1949-1991; for more detailed provenance information, consult the curator of the Yale Collection of American Literature.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Box 195: Restricted until 2025. For further information consult the appropriate curator. Boxes 196-200: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
THORNTON WILDER (1897-1975)
The life of Thornton Wilder has been documented in several books, including Richard Henry Goldstone's Thornton Wilder, an Intimate Portrait (Saturday Review Press, 1975); Linda Simon's Thornton Wilder: His World (Doubleday, 1979); and Gilbert A. Harrison's The Enthusiast (Ticknor & Fields, 1983). The following is a brief timeline pinpointing key events in his life: 1897 April 17, born in Madison, Wisconsin, 3rd child of Amos Parker Wilder and Isabel Niven Wilder. 1906 moves with family to Hong Kong when Amos is appointed American Consul General; returns with mother and children to Berkeley, California. 1911-1912 in China; attends China Inland Mission School in Chefoo, China. 1912-1913 attends Thacher School in Ojai, California. 1915 graduates from Berkeley High School, Berkeley, California. Enters Oberlin College in the fall. 1915-1917 Oberlin College. On Editorial Board of Oberlin Literary Magazine; publishes several short plays later collected in The Angel that Troubled the Waters. 1917 enters Yale College. 1918-1919 serves in U. S. Coast Guard Artillery for eight months. Returns to Yale. On Editorial Board of Yale Literary Magazine, which publishes his first long play, The Trumpet Shall Sound, as a serial. 1920 Graduates from Yale College. 1920-1921 at the American Academy in Rome; attends archaeology courses while writing The Cabala. 1921-1924 June Assistant Master in French at Lawrenceville School, New Jersey 1925 MA in French Literature, Princeton; summer at the MacDowell Colony. To Europe. 1926 In Europe; returns to Lawrenceville in the fall as Master of Davis House. The Cabala published. The Trumpet Shall Sound produced, American Laboratory Theatre, New York. 1927 November The Bridge of San Luis Rey published. 1928 The Bridge of San Luis Rey receives the Pulitzer Prize; The Angel that Troubled the Waters published. Resigns from Lawrenceville in June 1928 and travels to Europe. 1929 First major lecture tour on his return to the United States. 1930 The Woman of Andros published. Accepts appointment as lecturer in Comparative Literature, University of Chicago. 1930-1936 Teaches at Chicago for one semester each year; spends the remainder of the years on cross-country lecture tours and as a script writer in Hollywood. 1932 The Long Christmas Dinner published. 1933 Guest lecturer, University of Hawaii. Lucrece (adaptation of André Obey's Le viol de Lucrèce ) produced in New York by Guthrie McClintic and published. 1935 Heaven's My Destination published. Meets Gertrude Stein in Chicago. 1936 Resigns from University of Chicago and returns to Europe briefly. 1937 Adaptation of Ibsen's A Doll's House presented in New York by Jed Harris. 1938 Our Town produced by Jed Harris in Provincetown, Boston, and New York. Our Town receives the Pulitzer Prize. The Merchant of Yonkers opens in Boston in December, produced by the Theatre Guild. 1941 State Department cultural mission to Latin America; returns to England. Essay on James Joyce published in Poetry: A Magazine of Verse. Returns to the University of Chicago. 1942 Writes screenplay of "The Shadow of a Doubt" for Alfred Hitchcock. Enlists in Air Force and enters training in May. The Skin of Our Teeth opens in October in New Haven; in late November in New York. 1943 The Skin of Our Teeth receives the Pulitzer Prize. 1944-1945 Serves with U.S. Air Corps Intelligence in Africa and Italy. Receives rank of Lieutenant Colonel. Awarded Bronze Star, Legion of Merit, Military Order of the British Empire. Separated from service late 1945. 1948 The Ides of March published. 1949 Lectured Göethe Festival, Aspen, Colorado. 1950-1951 Holds Charles Eliot Norton Professorship at Harvard. Lectures on "The American Characteristics in Classic American Literature". 1952 Gold Medal for the novel, the American Academy of Arts and Letters. Chief of the American Delegation to the UNESCO Conference of the Arts, Venice. 1954 The Matchmaker premieres at the Edinburgh Festival in August and opens in London in November. 1955 The Alcestiad premieres at the Edinburgh Festival. The Matchmaker opens in New York in late November, produced by David Merrick. 1956-1962 Wilder travels frequently throughout the United States, making long stays in both Florida and Arizona. Continues to work on the libretto for the Alcestiad as well as on two cycles of one-act plays: The Seven Deadly Sins and The Long Christmas Dinner. 1958 Film of The Matchmaker appears. 1961 The Long Christmas Dinner, with music by Paul Hindemith, first produced in Germany. 1962 The Alcestiad, with music by Louise Talma, first produced in Germany. 1968 The Eighth Day published. 1973 Theophilus North published. 1975 December 7 Thornton Wilder dies in Hamden, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The Thornton Wilder Papers consist of correspondence, manuscripts, personal and business papers, printed material, photographs, memorabilia and audio tapes documenting the life and work of American author Thornton Wilder. The papers span the years 1900-1983, with the bulk of the material dating from the period 1935-1975.
The papers are housed in 210 boxes and are organized in eight series: Correspondence, Writings, Personal Papers, Printed Material, Photographs, Memorabilia and Other Papers, Audio Tapes and Other Recordings, and Thornton Wilder Papers Addition. Boxes 162-208 contain Oversize material, Restricted Material, and Restricted Fragile Papers.
Most of the papers now in the Thornton Wilder Papers (YCAL MSS 108) were the gift of Thornton Wilder or of family members; a small percentage were given to Yale before Wilder's death to be added to the collection, often at the request of Thornton or Isabel Wilder. The personal and family papers of other Wilder family members are found in the Wilder Family Papers (Uncat.ZA MS.455 and others); these materials, particularly those of his sister Isabel Wilder, inevitably contain much Wilder-related information. Material by or concerning Thornton Wilder acquired after his death in 1975 from sources other than the Wilder family is located in the Thornton Wilder Collection (YCAL MSS 162).
Series I, Correspondence, (boxes 1-67) is organized into four subseries: Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, First Name Only and Unidentified Correspondence, and Third-Party Correspondence.
Family Correspondence, which is housed in boxes 1-12, contains letters between Thornton Wilder, his parents and siblings, and several in-laws and cousins. Wilder wrote frequently to his parents throughout their lives, and his correspondence with Amos Parker Wilder and Isabel Niven Wilder is filled with reports on his education, reading, friendships and travel, and literary ambitions. Wilder's letters from Oberlin and Yale document his college experiences, classes, first publications, and reactions to World War I; subsequent letters offer news of his teaching jobs at Lawrenceville School and the University of Chicago, his initial trips to Europe and the composition of his novels, particularly The Cabala and The Bridge at San Luis Rey. The correspondence with Amos Parker Wilder in particular offers some of the younger Wilder's thoughts on religion and social conduct; letters to Isabel Niven Wilder often concern Wilder's health and recreational activities.
The fullest documentation of Wilder's life and thoughts during his long career as novelist and playwright, however, is found in his correspondence with his sister Isabel Wilder (boxes 3-9). Sharing the house on Deepwood Drive (which the family called "the house that The Bridge built") for almost 50 years, acting as his secretary, negotiator, and representative with fans, publishers, producers, and agents, and keeping Wilder's financial records in order as well, Isabel Wilder was in effect the manager of Wilder's literary success, and their extensive correspondence reflects this fact. The letters frequently contain Wilder's detailed instructions on everything from investment possibilities or the guest list for a New Year's Eve party through negotiating points for Isabel to make with producers and instructions for editorial changes by publishers. For example, the 1942-43 correspondence is filled with Wilder's comments on and directions for the New York production of The Skin of Our Teeth, as well as the reports Isabel sent to him from her attendance at the rehearsals and discussions with the director and the cast. During the 1950s and 1960s, when Wilder traveled frequently, his letters to Isabel contained both "personal" descriptions of his health, adventures and friends and "business" instructions on such matters as European royalty renegotiations for The Bridge of San Luis Rey and production changes Wilder desired in the Edinburgh Festival Alcestiad.
Wilder's correspondences with his brother Amos and sisters Charlotte and Janet are briefer and more often devoted to family news and plans for visits and reunions.
For additional correspondence between Wilder and family members, also see Series VIII, Thornton Wilder Papers Addition (boxes 209-210).
General Correspondence (boxes 13-65) contains mainly letters received by Wilder from the 1920s through the early 1970s, although the bulk of the letters date from the 1950s and 1960s. Some drafts of responses by Wilder survive, and some letters by Wilder were returned to the family and subsequently given by them to the library as part of the Thornton Wilder Papers.
In addition, Isabel Wilder managed most of Wilder's correspondence from the late 1940s until his death, particularly during Wilder's lengthy absences from their home in Hamden. She retained carbon copies of the letters she wrote for him (which often began, "My brother, Thornton Wilder, is in retirement..") and these are filed by recipient's name in the General Correspondence as well.
This subseries provides excellent documentation of Wilder's public reception and popularity during the decades following the premiere of Our Town. Much of the correspondence deals with requests for autographs, biographical information on Wilder, permissions to perform his plays, questions or comments on the "meaning" of his more popular works, and letters of general appreciation. Isabel Wilder's answers, often variations on a series of "standard" replies, demonstrate both Wilder's affection for his readers and his concern for the integrity of his works; permissions for amateur performances of Our Town, for example, were not easily obtained.
In addition to this large volume of "public" mail, the general correspondence also contains information on Wilder's personal and professional relationships. The correspondence of both Wilders with the literary agency Brandt & Brandt (boxes 17-27) provides a richly detailed overview of Wilder's success in both the United States and Europe. Further information on this subject can be found in the correspondence of publishers Albert and Charles Boni, Harper and Brothers and its successor house Harper & Row, Longmans, Green & Co., and Samuel French, Ltd; and in the files of Herbeth Herlitschka, who represented Wilder in Germany for many years.
Wilder's career in the theater is documented in his correspondences with Carol Channing, Sybil Colefax, Ruth Draper, Edith Evans, Mia Farrow, Ruth Gordon, Tyrone and Judith Guthrie, Garson Kanin, Vivien Leigh, Michael Myerberg, and Michael Redgrave. While the correspondence with Carol Channing is primarily social, there is discussion of Wilder's view of Hello, Dolly! (a musical adaptation of his The Matchmaker ). The letters of Myerberg are particularly informative about the difficult first production of The Skin of Our Teeth and the performance of Tallulah Bankhead as Sabrina. Montgomery Clift, who also appeared in that production, became a close personal friend of Wilder's during the 1940s; his letters are located in folder 693.
The letters of Louise Talma (folders 1602-1623) primarily concern her long and sometimes troubled collaboration with Wilder on the opera version of The Alcestiad.
Over the years, Wilder also developed friendships with a number of fellow writers, including Max Beerbohm, Robert Dodson, Mabel Dodge Luhan, Marcia Nardi, Vincent Sheehan, Gertrude Stein, Glenway Wescott, and Stark Young. Wilder's extensive correspondence with Stein (box 57) concerns his admiration of her work, personal news, reflections on writing and writers, including Joyce, politics, and her offer to collaborate with him on a novel (which he declined). The letters of Marcia Nardi contain typescripts of groups of poems she wanted Wilder to promote to publishers. Correspondence with Luhan and Wescott is primarily concerned with news of mutual friends and plans for visits.
Further biographical information on Wilder, as well as evidence of the considerable reservations of both Thornton and Isabel Wilder about interpretations of the author and his works, can be found in the correspondence with Wilder scholars C. Leslie Glenn, Malcolm Goldstein, Richard Goldstone, and Donald Haberman. The Goldstone files include third-party correspondence concerning his projected biography (later published as Thornton Wilder: An Intimate Portrait.
First Name Only and Unidentified Correspondence contains letters identified only by first name, arranged alphabetically, followed by unsigned and incomplete letters. Third-party correspondence includes letters by Walter de la Mare and Max Beerbohm.
Series II, Writings, (boxes 68-123) is organized into nine subseries: Plays: Original Works by Thornton Wilder, Plays: Adaptations by Wilder, Novels, Other Writings, Contributions to Works by Others, Reviews of Works by Others, Untitled Incomplete Writings, Writings of Others: On Thornton Wilder, and Writings of Others: Not Wilder-Related. Material in the first seven subseries has been arranged alphabetically by title and then by order of creation under each title. The last two contain material arranged alphabetically by author and where necessary by title.
Series II contains excellent documentation of Wilder's long career as a successful playwright and novelist, beginning with the publication of his first full-length play, The Trumpet Shall Sound (1926), and extending to the publication of Theophilus North, his final novel, in 1973. (Wilder's school and college productions can be found in Series III, Personal Papers, College Writings.) In addition, the Writings series also provides good evidence of the production history of his major plays and of the development of The Merchant of Yonkers into first The Matchmaker and ultimately into the Stewart and Herman musical Hello, Dolly!.
Material related to Wilder's first major stage success, Our Town, is located in boxes 78-82 and includes: holograph and typescript drafts, galley proofs of the first edition, production information related to the London production, and advertisements, playbills, and magazine and newspaper articles concerning the play collected by Wilder and his sister Isabel from 1938 to 1975. The lasting popularity of Our Town is also documented in the scripts and publicity material for films by Lesser and Schrank; radio adaptations, translations into several European languages, and other related material. Wilder's second Pulitzer-winning play, The Skin of Our Teeth, is represented by holographs, typescripts and galleys; production documentation; playbills and reviews; and articles concerning the 1942 charge of plagiarism made by Joseph Campbell and Henry Morton Robinson.
The original manuscript of The Merchant of Yonkers is found in folders 1892-1898. Also filed under this title are the manuscripts, typescripts and galleys of Wilder's own 1957 revision, The Matchmaker, and material relating to the 1966 musical version, Hello, Dolly!
Series II also contains manuscripts and related material for Wilder's other dramas, including the cycles The Seven Daily Sins and The Seven Ages of Man; drafts of "Three Minute Plays for Three Persons"; and drafts and notes for both the original version of The Long Christmas Dinner and the opera version by Paul Hindemith.
Although perhaps best-known for his plays, Wilder first drew attention as a novelist, and the Novels subseries contains drafts, galleys, reviews, publicity material and related items for all of his major works in that genre. The Bridge of San Luis Rey, which won the 1928 Pulitzer Prize for fiction, is represented by holograph manuscripts, proofs, advance copyright copies, book jackets, a printing history covering the period 1927-1949, theatrical versions and foreign translations, and even a set of Cliff Notes from 1966. Items related to other Wilder novels include a screenplay by Ruth Gordon based on Heaven's My Destination; a typescript for and Wilder's suggestions on Jerome Kilty's stage adaptation of The Ides of March; and a film treatment of Theophilus North.
The subseries Other Writings contains manuscripts, proofs, and printed copies of published lectures, including Wilder's Norton Lectures at Harvard; articles and article drafts on various topics; and notes and writings on Spanish playwright Lope de Vega.
Boxes 121-122 house Writings of Others: On Thornton Wilder, which includes typescript and printed articles by John Evarts, John Gassner, Richard Pini, Time magazine, and others. Writings of Others: Not Wilder-related consists mostly of offprints and printed copies of scholarly articles inscribed to Wilder by their authors, including Owen Dodson, Ralph Kirkpatrick, Ralph S. Lillie, and George W. Pierson. Folders 2818-2821 house the corrected and inscribed typescript of Georges Simenon's novel L'escalier de fer. A parody of one of Wilder's "Three Minute Plays", purportedly by Stephen Vincent Bénet, is located in Box 122, folder 2787.
Series III, Personal Papers (boxes 124-139), documents is organized into documents several aspects of Wilder's life and interests. most notably his college writing; his journaling and autobiographical writing; his teaching and public lecture career during the 1930s; and his military service from 1942 to 1945. The series is organized into eleven alphabetically arranged subseries: Appointment Books, Addresses, etc., Awards and Honors, Biographical Information, College Writings, Financial Papers, Journals and Autobiographical Writings, Lecture Outlines and Notes, Military Service Papers, Notes and Notebooks, Personal Appearances, and Travel Documents.
Awards and honors received by Wilder for his literary achievements and contributions are found in boxes 125-126. His changing financial situation during the course of his career is documented in the records located in boxes 128-130, including his annual "cash accounts" from 1928 to 1974, income tax information, various royalty statements, and miscellaneous bills and receipts.
The subseries College Writings, located in box 127, includes several compositions and short stories written during his time at Oberlin College, but the majority of the college compositions were written while Wilder was an undergraduate at Yale. In addition to the short stories and sketches Wilder produced during these years, the collection also contains Wilder's class themes for an American Literature survey course which he took in the spring of 1919. These brief essays contain Wilder's early verdicts on a range of classic American writers, from Washington Irving ("Statistics show that Washington Irving was one of the authors most cordially donated to the Camp Library Association. People fell over themselves in haste to discard Irving, Scott, and E. P. Roe") to Booth Tarkington ("The interest for me in reading Seventeen lies in discovering why it is not greater than it is.").